A wonderful dream, papa." I would sing it with the urgency and the burning desire of a nine-year-old who did, in fact, have a dream. My dream was to be an actress. And it's true that I never saw anyone who looked like me in television or in films, and sure, my family and friends and teachers all constantly warned me that people like me didn't make it in Hollywood. But I was an American. I had been taught to believe that anyone could achieve anything, regardless of the color of their skin, the fact that my parents immigrated from Honduras, the fact that I had no money. I didn't need my dream to be easy, I just needed it to be possible. And when I was 15, I got my first professional audition. It was a commercial for cable subscriptions or bail bonds, I don't really remember. (Laughter) What I do remember is that the casting director asked me,
Un sueño maravilloso, papá". Lo cantaba con la pasión y el deseo ardiente de una niña de nueve años que, de hecho, tenía un sueño. Mi sueño era ser actriz. Lo cierto es que nunca había visto a nadie parecido a mí en la televisión o en las películas, y es verdad que mi familia, amigos y maestros me advertían constantemente de que la gente como yo no triunfaba en Hollywood. Pero yo era estadounidense. Me habían enseñado a creer que cualquiera podía lograr lo que fuera, sin importar el color de la piel, el hecho de que mis padres fuesen inmigrantes hondureños o que no tuviera dinero. No necesitaba que mi sueño fuera fácil. Solo necesitaba que fuera posible. Con 15 años participé en mi primer casting profesional. Era un anuncio de tele por cable o de pagadores de fianzas, no lo recuerdo. (Risas) Lo que sí recuerdo es que el director del casting me pidió:
"Could you do that again, but just this time, sound more Latina." "Um, OK. So you want me to do it in Spanish?" I asked. "No, no, do it in English, just sound Latina." "Well, I am a Latina, so isn't this what a Latina sounds like?" There was a long and awkward silence, and then finally, "OK, sweetie, never mind, thank you for coming in, bye!" It took me most of the car ride home to realize that by "sound more Latina" she was asking me to speak in broken English. And I couldn't figure out why the fact that I was an actual, real-life, authentic Latina didn't really seem to matter. Anyway, I didn't get the job. I didn't get a lot of the jobs people were willing to see me for: the gang-banger's girlfriend, the sassy shoplifter, pregnant chola number two. (Laughter) These were the kinds of roles that existed for someone like me. Someone they looked at and saw as too brown, too fat, too poor, too unsophisticated. These roles were stereotypes and couldn't have been further from my own reality or from the roles I dreamt of playing. I wanted to play people who were complex and multidimensional, people who existed in the center of their own lives. Not cardboard cutouts that stood in the background of someone else's. But when I dared to say that to my manager -- that's the person I pay to help me find opportunity -- his response was, "Someone has to tell that girl she has unrealistic expectations." And he wasn't wrong. I mean, I fired him, but he wasn't wrong. (Laughter) (Applause) Because whenever I did try to get a role that wasn't a poorly written stereotype, I would hear, "We're not looking to cast this role diversely." Or, "We love her, but she's too specifically ethnic." Or, "Unfortunately, we already have one Latino in this movie." I kept receiving the same message again and again and again. That my identity was an obstacle I had to overcome. And so I thought, "Come at me, obstacle. I'm an American. My name is America. I trained my whole life for this, I'll just follow the playbook, I'll work harder." And so I did, I worked my hardest to overcome all the things that people said were wrong with me. I stayed out of the sun so that my skin wouldn't get too brown, I straightened my curls into submission. I constantly tried to lose weight, I bought fancier and more expensive clothes. All so that when people looked at me, they wouldn't see a too fat, too brown, too poor Latina. They would see what I was capable of. And maybe they would give me a chance. And in an ironic twist of fate, when I finally did get a role that would make all my dreams come true,
"¿Podrías repetirlo pero esta vez sonando más latina?" "Um. OK. ¿Quiere que lo diga en español?", pregunté. "No, no, en inglés, pero sonando más latina". "Bueno, soy latina, ¿no es así como suena una latina?". Tras un largo e incómodo silencio, finalmente dijo: "OK, cariño, no importa, gracias por venir, ¡adiós!" Tardé todo el trayecto de vuelta a casa en darme cuenta que con "sonar más latina" me estaba pidiendo que chapurrease el inglés. Y no entendía por qué el hecho de que yo era una latina auténtica, de carne y hueso, parecía no importar. De todos modos, no conseguí el trabajo. No conseguí muchos de los trabajos para los que la gente quería verme: la novia del pandillero, la ratera descarada, la chola preñada número dos. (Risas) Este era el tipo de papeles disponibles para alguien como yo. Alguien a quien miraban y consideraban demasiada morena, demasiada gorda, demasiada pobre, muy poco sofisticada. Estos papeles eran estereotipos y no podían estar más lejos de mi realidad o de los papeles que soñaba interpretar. Quería interpretar personajes complejos y multidimensionales, gente que existía en el centro de sus propias vidas. No figuras de cartón plantadas en el fondo de vidas ajenas. Pero cuando me atrevía a decírselo a mi representante, la persona a quien pagaba para que me ayudase a encontrar una oportunidad, su respuesta era: "Alguien debe decirle a esta chica que sus expectativas no son realistas". Y no se equivocaba. Lo despedí, pero no se equivocaba. (Risas) (Aplausos) Porque cuando trataba de conseguir un papel que no fuese un estereotipo, me decían: "No buscamos diversidad para este papel". O: "Nos encanta, pero es demasiada específica étnicamente hablando". O: "Por desgracia, ya tenemos un latino en esta película". Seguía recibiendo el mismo mensaje una y otra vez. Que mi identidad era un obstáculo que debía superar. Y entonces pensé: "Ven aquí, obstáculo. Soy estadounidense. Me llamo América. Me he preparado para esto toda mi vida, seguiré el guión y me esforzaré más. Y lo hice, me esforcé al máximo para superar todas las cosas de mí que la gente decía que estaban mal. Me alejaba del sol para que mi piel no se bronceara demasiado, alisé mis rizos para dominarlos. Intenté constantemente perder peso y compré ropa más cara y de moda. Todo para que al verme, la gente no viese a una latina demasiada gorda, morena y pobre. Verían de lo que era capaz. Y quizá me darían una oportunidad. En un irónico giro del destino, cuando finalmente conseguí un papel que haría mis sueños realidad,
it was a role that required me to be exactly who I was. Ana in "Real Women Have Curves" was a brown, poor, fat Latina. I had never seen anyone like her, anyone like me, existing in the center of her own life story. I traveled throughout the US and to multiple countries with this film where people, regardless of their age, ethnicity, body type, saw themselves in Ana. A 17-year-old chubby Mexican American girl
fue uno que requería que fuese exactamente quien yo era. Ana en "Las mujeres de verdad tienen curvas" era una latina morena, pobre y gorda. Nunca había visto a nadie como ella, a nadie como yo en el centro de su propia historia personal. Viajé por todo EE.UU. y a muchos países con esta película en la que la gente, sin importar la edad, etnia o tipo de cuerpo, se identificaba con Ana. Una joven mexicana regordeta de 17 años
struggling against cultural norms to fulfill her unlikely dream. In spite of what I had been told my whole life, I saw firsthand that people actually did want to see stories about people like me. And that my unrealistic expectations to see myself authentically represented in the culture were other people’s expectations, too. "Real Women Have Curves" was a critical, cultural and financial success. "Great," I thought, "We did it! We proved our stories have value. Things are going to change now." But I watched as very little happened.
que luchaba contra las normas culturales para cumplir su sueño improbable. A pesar de lo que me habían dicho toda mi vida, vi de primera mano que la gente quería ver historias sobre gente como yo. Y que mi expectativa poco realista de verme representada de verdad en la cultura también era la expectativa de muchos otros. "Las mujeres de verdad tienen curvas" fue un éxito de crítica, cultural y de recaudación. "Genial", pensé. "¡Lo logramos!" Demostramos que nuestras historias tenían valor. "Las cosas van a cambiar ahora". Pero vi que pasaban muy pocas cosas.
There was no watershed. No one in the industry was rushing to tell more stories about the audience that was hungry and willing to pay to see them. Four years later, when I got to play Ugly Betty, I saw the same phenomenon play out. "Ugly Betty" premiered in the US to 16 million viewers
No hubo un antes y un después. Nadie en la industria corría a contar más historias a un público hambriento y dispuesto a pagar para verlas. Cuatro años después, cuando protagonicé "Ugly Betty", vi como sucedía el mismo fenómeno. "Uggly Betty" se estrenó en EE.UU. para 16 millones de espectadores
and was nominated for 11 Emmys in its first year. (Applause) But in spite of "Ugly Betty's" success, there would not be another television show led by a Latina actress on American television for eight years. It's been 12 years since I became the first and only Latina to ever win an Emmy in a lead category. That is not a point of pride. That is a point of deep frustration. Not because awards prove our worth, but because who we see thriving in the world teaches us how to see ourselves, how to think about our own value, how to dream about our futures. And anytime I begin to doubt that, I remember that there was a little girl, living in the Swat Valley of Pakistan. And somehow, she got her hands on some DVDs of an American television show in which she saw her own dream of becoming a writer reflected. In her autobiography, Malala wrote, "I had become interested in journalism after seeing how my own words could make a difference and also from watching the "Ugly Betty" DVDs about life at an American magazine." (Applause) For 17 years of my career, I have witnessed the power our voices have when they can access presence in the culture. I've seen it. I've lived it, we've all seen it. In entertainment, in politics, in business, in social change. We cannot deny it -- presence creates possibility. But for the last 17 years, I've also heard the same excuses for why some of us can access presence in the culture and some of us can't. Our stories don't have an audience, our experiences won't resonate in the mainstream, our voices are too big a financial risk. Just a few years ago, my agent called to explain to me why I wasn't getting a role in a movie. He said, "They loved you and they really, really do want to cast diversely, but the movie isn't financeable until they cast the white role first." He delivered the message with a broken heart and with a tone that communicated, "I understand how messed up this is." But nonetheless, just like hundreds of times before, I felt the tears roll down my face. And the pang of rejection rise up in me and then the voice of shame scolding me, "You are a grown woman, stop crying over a job." I went through this process for years of accepting the failure as my own and then feeling deep shame that I couldn't overcome the obstacles. But this time, I heard a new voice. A voice that said, "I'm tired. I've had enough." A voice that understood my tears and my pain were not about losing a job. They were about what was actually being said about me. What had been said about me my whole life by executives and producers and directors and writers and agents and managers and teachers and friends and family. That I was a person of less value. I thought sunscreen and straightening irons would bring about change in this deeply entrenched value system. But what I realized in that moment was that I was never actually asking the system to change. I was asking it to let me in, and those aren't the same thing. I couldn't change what a system believed about me, while I believed what the system believed about me. And I did. I, like everyone around me, believed that it wasn't possible for me to exist in my dream as I was. And I went about trying to make myself invisible. What this revealed to me was that it is possible to be the person who genuinely wants to see change while also being the person whose actions keep things the way they are. And what it's led me to believe is that change isn't going to come by identifying the good guys and the bad guys. That conversation lets us all off the hook. Because most of us are neither one of those. Change will come when each of us has the courage to question our own fundamental values and beliefs. And then see to it that our actions lead to our best intentions. I am just one of millions of people who have been told that in order to fulfill my dreams, in order to contribute my talents to the world I have to resist the truth of who I am. I for one, am ready to stop resisting and to start existing as my full and authentic self. If I could go back and say anything to that nine-year-old, dancing in the den, dreaming her dreams, I would say, my identity is not my obstacle. My identity is my superpower. Because the truth is, I am what the world looks like. You are what the world looks like. Collectively, we are what the world actually looks like. And in order for our systems to reflect that, they don't have to create a new reality. They just have to stop resisting the one we already live in. Thank you. (Applause)
y fue nominada a 11 Emmy en su primer año. (Aplausos) A pesar del éxito de "Ugly Betty", no hubo otro programa de televisión protagonizado por una latina en la tele estadounidense durante 8 años. Han pasado 12 años desde que fui la primera y única latina en ganar un Emmy como protagonista. No es para estar orgulloso. Es para sentirse muy frustrado. No porque los premios demuestren nuestra valía, sino porque los que vemos triunfar en el mundo nos enseñan cómo nos vemos, cómo nos valoramos cómo soñar con el futuro. Cuando me asaltan las dudas, recuerdo que hubo una niña que vivía en el Valle de Swat, en Pakistán. De algún modo, llegaron a sus manos unos DVD de un programa estadounidense en el que vio reflejado su propio sueño de ser escritora. En su autobiografía, Malala escribió: "Me interesé por el periodismo tras ver cómo mis propias palabras podían marcar una diferencia y tras ver los DVD de "Uggly Betty" sobre la vida en una revista estadounidense". (Aplausos) Durante mis 17 años de trayectoria he sido testigo del poder de nuestras voces cuando tienen presencia en nuestra cultura. Lo he visto. Lo he vivido, todos lo hemos visto. En el mundo del entretenimiento, en la política, en los negocios, en los cambios sociales. Es innegable: la presencia crea posibilidades. Pero durante los últimos 17 años, también he oído las mismas excusas sobre por qué algunos de nosotros podemos estar presentes en la cultura y otros no. Nuestras historias no tienen público, nuestras experiencias no se reflejan en lo cotidiano, nuestras voces son un riesgo financiero muy alto. Hace unos años me llamó mi representante para explicarme por qué no me habían dado un papel. Dijo: "Les encantas, y están dispuestos a que el reparto sea diverso, pero no se puede financiar la película hasta que tengan a los actores blancos". Me transmitió el mensaje con el corazón roto y con un tono que venía a decir: "Sé lo mal que está esto". Sin embargo, como otros cientos de veces, sentí las lágrimas rodar por mis mejillas. La angustia por el rechazo se alzó dentro de mí y oí la voz de la vergüenza regañándome: "Eres una mujer adulta, no llores por un trabajo". Durante años sufrí este proceso de aceptar los fracasos como propios y luego sentir una profunda vergüenza por no poder superar los obstáculos. Pero esta vez, oí una nueva voz. Una voz que decía: "Estoy harta. Ya basta". Una voz que comprendía que mis lágrimas y mi dolor no eran por perder un trabajo. Era por lo que en realidad decían de mí. Lo que habían dicho de mí toda la vida ejecutivos y productores, directores, escritores, agentes, representantes, profesores y familiares. Que yo era alguien con menos valor. Pensé que la crema de protección solar y las planchas alisadoras supondrían un cambio en este rígido sistema de valores. Pero entonces me di cuenta, de que nunca había pedido al sistema que cambiase. Le pedía que me dejara entrar, y eso no es lo mismo. No podía cambiar lo que el sistema creía sobre mí, mientras yo creía lo que el sistema creía sobre mí. Y lo hice. Yo, como todos los de mi alrededor, creía que no era posible que existiese en mi sueño tal y como era. Por eso intenté hacerme invisible. Lo que esto me reveló es que es posible ser la persona que de verdad desea ver un cambio mientras se es una persona cuyas acciones mantienen las cosas como son. Y eso me ha llevado a creer que el cambio no vendrá identificando los buenos y los malos. Esa perspectiva nos salva a todos. Porque la mayoría no somos ni lo uno ni lo otro. El cambio vendrá cuando todos tengamos el coraje de cuestionarnos nuestros propios valores y creencias fundamentales. Y ver que nuestras acciones conducen a nuestras mejores intenciones. Soy solo una de los millones de personas a quienes se les han dicho que para cumplir sus sueños, para contribuir al mundo con sus talentos, deben resistir a lo que son realmente. Sé que estoy lista para dejar de resistir y empezar a existir como mi yo pleno y auténtico. Si pudiera volver atrás y decirle algo a esa niña de nueve años que bailaba en el salón, soñando, le diría: mi identidad no es mi obstáculo. Mi identidad es mi superpoder. Porque lo cierto es que soy lo que el mundo es. Uds. son lo que el mundo es. Colectivamente, todos somos lo que el mundo es en realidad. Y para que nuestros sistemas reflejen esto, ellos no tienen que crear una nueva realidad. Solo tienen que dejar de resistirse a aquella en la que ya viven. Gracias. (Aplausos)